Guide to the Fawn McKay Brodie audio-visual collection 1946-1995 1971-1980
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Fawn McKay Brodie audio-visual collection
1946-1995
1971-1980
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 801-581-8864 http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/
A0026
Brodie, Fawn McKay, 1915-1981
61 audiocassettes, 1 reel-to-reel audiotape, 3 norelco microcassettes, 1 U-matic videocassette
The Fawn McKay Brodie audio-visual collection (1946-1995, bulk 1971-1980) consists primarily of oral history interviews with people associated with President Richard Nixon, his life, his administartion, and the controversies surrounding it. Brodie conducted these interviews as part of the research for her 1981 book, Richard Nixon: The Shaping of his Character. In addition to Brodie's own interviews, the collection also contains archived dictation and radio news reports used by Brodie in her research, as well as a television interview with Brodie and a recording of her 1978 lecture, Nixon: The Child and the Man and other material relating to Brodie's works and interests. Utah native Fawn Brodie was a history professor and biographer who published several books about historical figures, including Thomas Jefferson and Joseph Smith.
Biographical Note
Fawn McKay Brodie (1915-1981) was born Fawn McKay in Ogden, Utah and grew up in nearby Huntsville. She earned a Bachelor of Arts degree in English Literature from the University of Utah in 1934 and in 1936 completed a Master of Arts degree at the University of Chicago, where she met and married Bernard Brodie. After graduation began researching the history of the Book of Mormon and, in 1945, published No Man Knows My History: The Life of Joseph Smith, which resulted in her 1946 excommunication from Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
After publishing two more biographies, Thaddeus Stevens: Scourge of the South (1959) and The Devil Drives: A Life of Sir Richard Burton (1967), Brodie began to teach history and American political biography at the University of California Los Angeles (UCLA). Thomas Jefferson: An Intimate History was published in 1974 and Richard Nixon: The Shaping of His Character in late 1981, nine monts after her death from lung cancer earlier that year.
The Fawn McKay Brodie audio-visual collection (1946-1995, bulk 1971-1980) consists primarily of oral history interviews with people associated with President Richard Nixon, his life, his administartion, and the controversies surrounding it. Brodie conducted these interviews as part of the research for her 1981 book, Richard Nixon: The Shaping of his Character. In addition to Brodie's own interviews, the collection also contains archived dictation and radio news reports used by Brodie in her research, as well as a television interview with Brodie and a recording of her 1978 lecture, Nixon: The Child and the Man and other material relating to Brodie's works and interests. Unless otherwise noted, all materials in this collection have been digitized and are available on compact disc or DVD.
Materials are arranged in the order of their original donation.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
Donated by Pamela Brodie and Bruce Brodie in 1982 and Steve Mayfield in 1999.
See also the Fawn McKay Brodie papers (Ms 360) and photograph collection (P0026).
Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Kissinger, Henry, 1923-; History, 20th Century--United States; Oral history; Political Campaigns; Moving Images; Sound Recordings; Oral Histories; Moving images; Sound recordings
- Nixon: The Child and the Man lecture, 1978 October 19; Audiocassette (Cassette 1)
- KUTV News interview with Fawn Brodie about her work on Joseph Smith, circa 1971; U-matic videocassettes (Cassette 2)
- John Dean, 1977 June 22; Audiocassette (Cassette 3)
- Jack Anderson, 1975 April 19; Audiocassette (Cassette 4)
- General Robert Cushman, 1978 June; Audiocassette (Cassette 5)
- Bob Finch, 1977 March; Audiocassette (Cassette 6)
- Helmut Sommerfeldt, 1977 March 14; Audiocassette (Cassette 7)
- Bob Woodward, 1980 April 06; Audiocassette (Cassette 8)
- Martin Agronsky, Henry Kissinger, Channel 28, 1977 January 11; Audiocassette (Cassette 9)
- Richard Bergholz, Los Angeles Times, 1980 April 01; Audiocassette (Cassette 10)
- Thomas Bewley, 1976 April 15; Audiocassette (Cassette 11)
- Richard Bissell, 1977 March 28; Audiocassette (Cassette 12)
- Pat Brown (Edmund G.), Beverly Hills, 1976 April 15; Audiocassette (Cassette 13)
- Lou Cannon, Washington Post, 1980 April 28; Audiocassette (Cassette 14)
- Kenneth Chotener (Murray Chotner's son), Santa Monica, 1978 February 18; Audiocassette (Cassette 15-16)
- Judge James Cobey, Undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 17)
- Reverand Coffin, Last Whittier Quaker Church, 1976 April 15; Audiocassette (Cassette 18)
- Roy Coln, New York City Eye and Ear Hospital, 1979 April 26; Audiocassette (Cassette 19)
- Tom Dixon, KFAC Radio Los Angeles, 1975 November 28; Audiocassette (Cassette 20)
- Evelyn Dorn, Nixon's Whittier secretary, 1946 April 13; Audiocassette (Cassette 21)
- Eugene Genoresa, Los Angeles, 1977 November 06; Audiocassette (Cassette 22)
- Bob Green, Newsday, Rokonhoma, New York, 1977 March 30; Audiocassette (Cassette 23)
- Haldiman-Wallace, Undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 24)
- Leonard Wood Hall, Garden City, New York, 1975 August 20; Audiocassette (Cassette 25)
- Hess, Undated; Norelco microcassette (Cassette 26-27)
  These interviews were recorded on a format not supported by our archive and are not available on compact disc at this time.
- Stephen Hess, 1978 February 01; Audiocassette (Cassette 28)
- Phoebe Howard (Elizabeth Evans' sister), 1976 November 21; Audiocassette (Cassette 29)
- Henry Kissinger and Dan Frost, 1979 October 11; Audiocassette (Cassette 30)
- Henry Kissinger lecture dictation, 1968 April 04; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 31)
- Herb Klein, 1977 March 22; Audiocassette (Cassette 32-33)
- Anthony Lewis, New York Times, Boston, 1977 March 28; Audiocassette (Cassette 34)
- Rose Olive and O. Marshburn (Nixon's aunt and uncle), Whittier, 1977 April 30; Audiocassette (Cassette 35)
- Dick Mathis, Los Angeles, 1977 August 19; Audiocassette (Cassette 36)
- Unidentified Nixon associate, Undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 37)
- CBS News coverage of Nixon's resignation speech; statement by Gerald Ford, 1974 August 08; Audiocassette (Cassette 38)
- NBC News coverage of Nixon's farewell speech with commentary; Gerald Ford's inauguration, 1977 August 19; Audiocassette (Cassette 39)
- Nixon interview with Frost, 1977 May 04; 1977 May 12; 1977 May 19; 1977 May 25; 1977 September 05; Audiocassette (Cassette 40-44)
- Nixon and Dunpey, 1979 November 26; Audiocassette (Cassette 45-46)
- Nixon Melhouse film, Undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 47)
- William Purdue, New York, 1976 November 05; Audiocassette (Cassette 48)
- Judge J. Pasht, 1976 October 03; Audiocassette (Cassette 49)
- Dan Rather, CBS, New York, 1975 August 30; Audiocassette (Cassette 50)
- James Reston, Jr., University of California Los Angeles (UCLA), 1977 April 21; Audiocassette (Cassette 51)
- Ed Rubin, Undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 52)
- Mrs. Foster (Georgia) Sherwood, 1973 October 10; Audiocassette (Cassette 53)
- Ralph de Toledano, 1975 August 30; Audiocassette (Cassette 54-55)
- Jerry Voorkis, Claremont, 1978 February 22; Audiocassette (Cassette 56)
- Jessamyn West (cousin of Richard Nixon) at home of her brother, Merle West, in Hacienda Heights, 1976 September 29; Audiocassette (Cassette 57-58)
- Paul Ziffren, 1976 December 18; Audiocassette (Cassette 59)
- George Reedy at Marquette University, 1977 March 25; Audiocassette (Cassette 60)
- Stephen Hess, Undated; Norelco microcassette (Cassette 61)
- Discussion of future of higher education in the sate of Utah, 1974; Audiocassette (Cassette 62)
- "Fawn Brodie Symposium: No Man Knows My History", 1995 August; Audiocassette (Cassette 63-66)
  Presenters include Martha Bradley, Linda K. Newell, Newell Bringhurst, Mario dePillis, Roger Launius, William Mulder, Laivinia Fielding Anderson, Mauricio Mazon, Todd Compton. Also includes August 6, 1995, radio interview with Newell Bringhurst on KTKK radio.